

Joaquín Delgado Fernández Ph.D. Computer Science



Luxembourg, Luxembourg



+34 648113796 +33 (0)767916948



joaquindf



jdfdelgadofe96@gmail.com

Skills -

Artificial Intelligence

Machine Learning

Time series analysis

Communication Skills

**Analytical Modelling** 

Critical Thinking

Languages -

Spanish

English

French

#### About me

As a Ph.D. in Computer Science and accomplished Software Engineer, I've had the privilege of serving as a Researcher at the Interdisciplinary Center for Security, Reliability, and Trust (SnT), University of Luxembourg. My specialization lies in distributed computing, with a strong emphasis on advanced machine learning applications for energy systems.

Throughout my academic and professional journey, I've gained extensive experience in machine learning applications, with a primary focus on enhancing distributed machine learning technologies.

My research has made a significant impact in the energy sector, where I work diligently to improve load forecasting, as well as in the financial sector, where I've led innovations in credit risk assessment.

### Experience

2023

Postdoctoral Researcher

SnT - University of Luxembourg - Luxembourg

- Forefront of the energy revolution through advanced AI techniques.
- Collaborating closely between the SnT and Lead Energy supplier in Luxembourg.
- Use of AI and machine learning to reduce forecasting errors and enhance energy supply and demand dynamics.
- Write and evaluate national (FR, LUX) and international (EU) research proposals.

2020 - 2023

**Doctoral Researcher** 

SnT - University of Luxembourg - Luxembourg

- Close collaboration with energy and financial experts from both industry and academia.
- Development of time-series models in the University of Luxembourg's High Performance Computer (HPC).
- Project management duties of a large European consortium.
- Write national and international (EU) research proposals.

2019 - 2020

Data Scientist

Shift Technology - Paris, France

- Representing the Shift product from a technical point of view to customers, including demonstrations, conducting proofof-concept trials, helping clients evaluate success criteria, and training users.
- Presentation of results to steering committees and performance reviews.
- Participation in workshops with clients to collect feedback and integrate it into models.
- Pre-sales of products to new potential clients all over the world.

2018 - 2019

International Graduate Consultant

The AKKAdemy - Geneva/Lyon

- Development of a Collision Avoidance and Emergency Break Algorithm for Autonomous Vehicles on behalf of Akka Research
- Full-time applied training on: Agile methods, stakeholder management, innovation strategy, risk management, customer analysis

2017 - 2018

Artificial Intelligence Intern BISITE Research Group - Salamanca, Spain Machine Learning techniques and data analysis for Business Intelligence

Education

2023 PhD. Computer Science

University of Luxembourg

Thesis title: Breaking data silos with Federated Learning -

Nominated for the Best thesis award

2019 M.Sc. Artificial Intelligence

International University of La Rioja

2018 B.Eng. Computer Science engineering

University of Salamanca

2016 Computer Science engineering

University of Wolverhampton

Erasmus Exchange Programme (Full Year)

### Published articles

Fernández, J. D., Menci, S. P., Lee, C. M., Rieger, A., & Fridgen, G. (2022). Privacy-preserving federated learning for residential short-term load forecasting.

Applied Energy - Top 1 % Journal

Fernández, J. D., Menci, S. P., Lee, C. M., Rieger, A., & Fridgen, G. (2022). Federated Learning for Credit Risk Assessment.

HICSS - A1 Conference

Sprenkamp, K., Fernández, J. D., Eckhardt, S., & Zavolokina, L. (2023, January). Federated Learning as a Solution for Problems Related to Intergovernmental Data Sharing.

HICSS - A1 Conference

Fernández, J. D., Menci, S. P., Pavic, I. (2022). Towards a peer-to-peer residential short-term load forecasting with federated learning.

Forthcoming - PowerTech

# Under review Publications

Fernández, J. D., Willburger, L., Wiethe, C., Wenninger, S., & Fridgen, G. (2022). Scaling smart cities with federated learning – balancing accuracy and privacy for building energy performance prediction.

Under review - Top 1 % journal

Lee, C. M., Fernández, J. D., Barbereau, T., & Fridgen, G. (2022). Federated Learning.

Under review - 88 % journal

Fernández, J. D., Barbereau, T., & Papageorgiou, O. (2022). Agent-based Model of Initial Token Allocations: Evaluating Wealth Concentration in Fair Launches.

Under review - 88 % journal

## Presentations and other activities

2023 Revision of research proposals for the Agence nationale de la re-

cherche (ANR)

SnT University of Luxembourg

2023 Federated Learning in the new banking sector

Stuttgart Stock Exchange

2022 Federated Learning for Problems Related to Intergovernmental Da-

ta Sharing

**ESCAP United Nations** 

2022 Federated Learning for Credit Risk Assessment

Financial Innovation Hub - SnT University of Luxembourg